Finding Aid for High/Scope Educational Research Foundation Records 1963-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
High/Scope Educational Research Foundation Records 1963-2000
High/Scope Educational Research Foundation.
Independent, non-profit organization founded by Dr. David P. Weikart, whose purpose is to promote the learning and development of young people from infancy through adolescence, with emphasis on early childhood education. Project files consisting of proposals relating to preschool education; Follow Through project materials and issues of their summer camp's newsletter; administrative files consisting of annual reports, board of directors meeting minutes, financial reports, and directors correspondence.
90179; Bi 2
22.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated in June 1990 by High/Scope (Donor No. 7814 ). Additional records were received in 2002.
The record group is open for research.
The High/Scope Educational Research Foundation of Ypsilanti, Michigan is an independent, non-profit organization whose purpose is to promote the learning and development of young people from infancy through adolescence, with a special emphasis on early childhood education. High/Scope engages in research, curriculum development, publishing, and policy work, and also provides technical assistance and professional training to those directly involved in childhood education.
Although High/Scope was not formally established until 1970, many of its long-term projects were initiated during the early 1960s. High/Scope's founder and president, Dr. David P. Weikart, directed several well-known early childhood education projects through the Ypsilanti Public Schools and Eastern Michigan University during that time. The difficulty of coordinating large-scale projects through two separate institutions and the realization that this work was becoming increasingly national and international in scope led to the establishment of High/Scope as an independent organization in 1970.
Weikart's early work at Ypsilanti coincided with a period of change in educational research and of renewed governmental emphasis on combating poverty and welfare dependency. During the early 1960s, educational researchers began to challenge the idea of predetermined and fixed cognitive development in children. They emphasized the impact of the environment, and stressed that cognitive development occurred most rapidly during the preschool years. At the same time, the "war on poverty" initiated by the Kennedy and Johnson administrations placed a high priority on the prevention of adult poverty through assistance to disadvantaged children. This combination of events set the stage for federal funding for early childhood education programs for the disadvantaged, such as the National Head Start Program (begun in 1965).
Weikart's Ypsilanti Perry Preschool Project (1962-1967) was one of the pioneering independent programs for disadvantaged children, and reflected the new directions in educational research. The Preschool was begun in response to studies which found that some children were entering school with cognitive deficiencies which limited their ability to benefit from the existing school system. Although the Perry Preschool was not a Head Start program, it did receive federal funding in its later years, and its structure was very similar to the Head Start programs. For this reason, the various long-term studies conducted by High/Scope of the Perry Preschool Project have played an important role in the ongoing discussion of the effectiveness of Head Start programs.
During the Perry Preschool Project the Ypsilanti staff developed a cognitively oriented curriculum, based on the theories of Jean Piaget, which has been developed and refined over the years by High/Scope and is the basis for High/Scope's current training efforts. This curriculum encourages active learning, in which children are encouraged to initiate their own activities, and the teacher acts as facilitator and catalyst. The teacher encourages the development of specific thinking and reasoning skills, which are linked to the various stages in child development.
Short-term evaluation of the Perry Preschool Project led to further research by the Ypsilanti staff in three specific areas. Further preschool research was undertaken, in the form of the Preschool Curriculum Demonstration Project (1967), which compared a cognitive, a language, and a traditional curriculum to see which would be more effective. Also, the Ypsilanti staff began participation in the National Planned Variation Head Start Program in 1969. The cognitive curriculum was one of twelve to be tested in this program, and was operated in four remote sites.
Since some preschoolers had not responded as well as expected to the Perry Preschool Project, the second direction of research was toward intervention at the infant level. The Ypsilanti Home Teaching Project (1966) tested the feasibility of home teaching, and its favorable results led to the Ypsilanti Carnegie Infant Project, which began in 1967. This program was continued in 1971 by the Infant Video-Taping Project, which recorded home teaching sessions in order to make instructional tapes. The third phase of the project concentrated on training mothers as home teachers, so that they could in turn train others. Encouraging parent involvement and training teachers has continued to be a primary goal of High/Scope's staff through the 1970s and 1980s.
The third direction of research resulted from indications that preschool gains tended to be lost in later grades. In 1968, High/Scope became involved in the National Follow Through Program, covering kindergarten through third grade. The High/Scope curriculum was administered at three remote sites during the first year (Harlem, New York City; Okaloosa County, Florida; and Leflore County, Mississippi), and seven new sites were added the following year (Chicago; The Central Ozarks, Missouri; Riverton, Wyoming; Trinidad, Greeley, and Denver, Colorado; and Seattle, Washington). High/Scope's involvement in the Follow Through program continues to the present day. Over the years High/Scope has also expanded its activities to include adolescents, beginning operation of a yearly summer camp in Michigan for teenagers in 1963.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s one of High/Scope's highest priorities has been research. High/Scope has conducted studies not only of its own projects, but also for various federal agencies, the State of Michigan, and a number of public school districts. Since 1984, a major research effort has been the IEA Preprimary Study (sponsored by the International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement). High/Scope serves as headquarters and coordinating center for the study, which explores the types of childcare provided in 17 different countries and will then integrate the 17 national studies. High/Scope's participation in international childhood education in fact dates from the early 1970s, when it began to provide consulting services, training, and workshops to several Latin American countries.
High/Scope has also continued to develop its Cognitive Curriculum, to train teachers in this curriculum, and to inform the public about programs for children and their families. High/Scope holds workshops at its Training and Development Center in Ypsilanti and elsewhere, participates in a graduate program in education and human development, and conducts Training of Teacher-Trainers Programs throughout the country, which provide training in the High/Scope curriculum to educators who will then become trainers themselves. High/ Scope's Policy Center provides outreach to educators, policymakers, researchers, and the public, and the High/Scope Press publishes books, records, audiovisual programs and curriculum materials.
The High/Scope Educational Foundation records have been divided into three series, Project Files, Administrative Files and President Records. A folder of historical materials has been placed at the beginning of the record group. In general, the records consist of grant proposals, correspondence, reports, and publications created by the Foundation and its founder, Dr. David P. Weikart.
Subjects:
Education, Preschool.; Follow Through Program (U.S.); Head Start programs--Michigan.; High/Scope Educational Research Foundation.; Project Follow Through.; Project Head Start (U.S.)
Contributors:
Weikart, David P.
- High/Scope historical materials
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Project Files 1963-1988
  The Project Files series includes project proposals, reports, and founding sources. It also contains records regarding the Follow Through Program for kindergarten through grade three, one of the main programs developed by High/Scope. The project is extensively documented, with materials running through the 1970s and scattered materials covering the early 1980s. This series also documents the High/Scope's consulting services, training, and workshops in Latin America and Europe.
  - Proposals 1963-1978
    - 1963-1968
      - Intervention in the Cognitive Development of the Culturally Deprived Negro Preschool Child 1963 (Box 1)
      - Development of a Curriculum to Prepare Mentally Handicapped Girls in High School for the Child Rearing Role 1965 (Box 1)
      - Ypsilanti Preschool Curriculum Demonstration Project 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1969
      - Contract for Development of an Instrument for Measuring Maternal and Child Behavior Scales (Box 1)
      - Evaluation of Teacher Corps (Box 1)
      - Head Start Model Project (Box 1)
      - Ypsilanti-State of Michigan Preschool Demonstration Project (Box 1)
      - Ypsilanti Carnegie Infant Education Project (Box 1)
    - 1970
      - Filming Grant for Ypsilanti Carnegie Infant Education Project (Box 1)
    - 1971
      - High/Scope Model Preschool Program (Box 1)
      - High/Scope Parent-Child Development Center, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Parent-Child Education Project (Box 1)
      - Spencer Foundation Proposals (Box 1)
      - Teacher Corps (Box 1)
    - 1972
      - Evaluation of the Fifth City Preschool Program (Box 1)
      - Introductory Film for the Training of Teachers in the High/Scope Preschool Program (Box 1)
      - Preliminary Plan for Providing 1) Child-rearing Information to Parents and 2) Training to Preschool/Day Care Teachers and Aides via an Interactive Cable TV System (Box 1)
      - Preparation of Leadership Personnel in Preschool Education for the Handicapped (Box 1)
    - 1973
      - Designing a System for the Collection, Storage and Reporting of Information for Detroit Head Start (Draft) (Box 1)
      - Infant Education Demonstration Project (Box 1)
      - Production of Multi-media Models for Child Development Associates Preparation (Box 1)
      - Remodeling of the High/Scope Foundation's Training and Development Center (Box 1)
      - Training Materials Development for Health and Psychological Professions (Box 1)
    - 1974
      - A Comparison of Some Representative Approaches to Spanish-English Elementary Education (Box 1)
      - Conduct Experimental Schools Level III Evaluation (Box 1)
      - Conduct Workshops and Develop Materials to Assist Head Start Supplementary Training Programs Implement CDA Competency-Based Training, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Demonstration Project to Test a Training/Delivery Model for Infant Education (Box 2)
      - Development of Mediated Programs for the Handicapped (Box 2)
      - Family vs. School Expectations (Box 2)
      - A Longitudinal Study of the Development of Writing and Its Relation to the Development and Application of Fundamental Cognitive Processes (Box 2)
      - Training Program for Chilean Educators (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Small Proposals 1974-1978 (Box 2)
      - Peer-to-Peer: A Paradigm of Change 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - Florida Center for Children and Youth 1986 (Box 2)
  - Follow Through Program
    - The Ypsilanti Follow Through Model: Cognitively Oriented Curriculum undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, Charles Wallgren 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Curriculum materials
      - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
      - 1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Guidelines and history
      - 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - undated (Box 2)
    - Implementation
      - Implementation Studies 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - Ratings of Follow Through Classrooms on the Implementation Matrix 1973 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1980-1988 (Box 3)
    - National Network 1979 (Box 3)
    - Program Advocacy 1977-1980 (Box 3)
    - Project Phase-In 1974 (Box 3)
    - Proposals
      - An Alternative Evaluation Procedure to Assess Language Arts Achievement 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - Continuation Proposals 1969-1985, 10 folders (Box 3)
      - Proposal for a Joint Model Study Project, High/Scope and University of Kansas 1978 (Box 3)
      - Provide Planning Information for Follow Through Experiments 1978 (Box 3)
      - Training Program for the Cognitively Oriented Ypsilanti Follow Through Model 1969 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - Annual Report 1973 (Box 3)
      - Advisory Committee Report 1973 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum and Program Reports 1971-1977, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Field Service Reports 1972-1974, 7 folders (Box 12)
      - Mid Year Review 1971 (Box 12)
      - Progress Reports
        - 1970 (Box 12)
        - Sponsor Evaluation Activities: Formative and Summative 1973, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Reports on Follow Through Working Conferences 1968, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
    - Sponsor Communication Advisory Network
      - Cross-Sponsor Conference 1977 (Box 12)
      - Executive Committee 1978-1979 (Box 12)
      - Messages sent via SCAN 1973-1979 (Box 12)
      - Sponsor Conferences
        - 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Subcontracts 1972-1978 (Box 13)
  - Funding
    - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation
      - Correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 13)
      - Proposal: Teacher Trainer Intern Program for School Systems 1975 (Box 13)
    - Ford Foundation
      - Correspondence 1971-1992, 6 folders (Box 13)
      - Proposals
        - H/S Educational Research Foundation Registration and Accreditation Council 1986 (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1976 1985 (Box 13)
          - 1986-1987 (Box 13)
      - The Training of Teacher-Trainers Project
        - Proposals 1986-1987 (Box 13)
        - Report April 26, 1989 (Box 13)
      - Grant Foundation Inc.
        - Report on the Staff Training and Curriculum Development Center 1974 (Box 13)
      - W. K. Kellogg Foundation
        - Family Voluntarism Project
          - Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 13)
        - Training of Teacher-Trainers in Michigan Project: Report 1990, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - International Projects
    - British High/Scope Training Programme Final Report 1986 (Box 13)
    - Chile 1971-1974 (Box 13)
    - Colombia 1971-1974, 2 folders (Box 13)
      (includes an audiocassette)
    - International Association for the Evaluation of Educational Achievement 1983-1986, 1991 (Box 14)
    - Study Centre for Children Activities, Oranim, School of Education, Israel 1977 (Box 14)
    - Trinidad-Tobago 1994 (Box 14)
  - Reports
    - A Research Plan for Spelling Reform 1987 (Box 14)
    - Child Study Association of America/We-Met Inc. 1974 (Box 14)
    - Review of the Extended Elementary Education Program 1984 (Box 14)
    - Infant Videotaping Project 1973 (Box 14)
    - KIDS Program undated (Box 14)
    - Maine's Expansion of Head Start Services 1986 (Box 14)
    - The Cognitively Oriented Curriculum 1970-1972 (Box 14)
    - Ypsilanti Carnegie Infant Education Project
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 1973-1974, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Ypsilanti Preschool Curriculum Demonstration Project
      - Reports
        - 1967-1970 (Box 14)
          no reports for 1968
        - 1972 1974 (Box 14)
      - Evaluations 1968-1969 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous Reports undated (Box 14)
  - Ypsilanti Perry Preschool Project
    - Project Information 1971, 1979, 1983, 2000 (Box 14)
    - Progress Reports 1963-1964 (Box 14)
    - Final Report: Longitudinal Results of the Ypsilanti Perry Preschool Project 1970 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Birmingham Parent Child Development Center 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Child Observation Record and Child Assessment Record, Manual 1987 (Box 4)
    - Panopticon
      - Volume 1 1963 (Box 4)
      - Volume 2 1964 (Box 4)
      - Volume 3 1965 (Box 4)
      - Volume 4 1966 (Box 4)
      - Volume 5 1967 (Box 4)
      - Volume 6 1968 (Box 4)
      - Volume 7 1969 (Box 4)
      - Volume 8 1970 (Box 4)
      - Volume 9 1971 (Box 4)
      - Volume 10 1972 (Box 4)
      - Volume 11 1973 (Box 4)
      - Volume 12 1974 (Box 4)
      - Volume 13 1975 (Box 4)
- Administrative files
  The Administrative Files series contains annual reports, meeting minutes, and financial reports. Taken together these materials cover the entire chronology of High/Scope's activities. Most valuable is the run of board of directors meeting minutes, covering the period 1970 to 1998. Financial statements are included for the years 1970 through 1989. Also included in this series are weekly announcement bulletins which provide a look at the day-to-day activities of the Foundation.
  - Announcement Bulletins 1987-1990, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1970-1976, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Meetings
    - Board of Directors
      - 1970-1971, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - 1972-1983, 34 folders (Box 5)
      - 1984-1990, 17 folders (Box 6)
      - 1993 (Box 6)
      - 1995-1998, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Departmental Coordination Meetings 1971-1980, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Michigan's Children First Annual Board Meeting 1993 (Box 15)
    - Supervisor's Meetings 1970-1971 (Box 15)
    - United Kingdom Board Meetings
      - 1992-1995, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - 1997 (Box 15)
  - Financial Statements
    - 1970-1985, 15 folders (Box 15)
    - 1985-1989, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Goals 1979-1980 (Box 11)
  - Inter Office Memos 1974-1983, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - Publicity Materials undated (Box 11)
- President Records, David P. Weikart
  The President Records series is arranged alphabetically by topic and contains biographical information, correspondence, and writings and speeches of Dr. David Weikart, founder and President Emeritus of High/Scope Educational Research Foundation. The director's correspondence is the largest group of material within this series, and remains in its original order. Early correspondence covering the period 1965-1982 is arranged chronologically by fiscal year (July-June) and then (if warranted by size) alphabetically. Recent correspondence (since 1983) is arranged alphabetically and then by chronological subdivisions. A subseries of international correspondence is included in this series and is arranged alphabetically by the name of the country.
  Weikart's writings and speeches include articles published, books, chapters published, High/Scope papers, speeches and presentations, and miscellaneous papers. These writings and speeches document both theoretical and practical information regarding High/Scope and educational topics studied by Dr. Weikart.
  - Biographical Information 1977 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Perry Preschool Project 1965-1966 (Box 7)
    - Early Correspondence 1965-1982
      - 1965-1970, 8 folders (Box 7)
      - 1970-1971
        - A-F (Box 7)
        - Far West Laboratory for Educational Research and Development 1970 (Box 7)
        - G-Z, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1971-1972
        - A-C (Box 7)
        - D-Z, 7 folders (Box 8)
      - 1972-1974, 12 folders (Box 8)
      - 1974-1975
        - A-J, 9 folders (Box 8)
        - K-Z, 8 folders (Box 9)
      - 1975-1976
        - A-K, 6 folders (Box 9)
        - Kleber, Charles (Box 9)
        - L-Z, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - 1976-1977, 8 folders (Box 9)
      - 1977-1978
        - A-C (Box 9)
        - Carnegie Corporation (Box 9)
        - D-H (Box 9)
        - I-Z, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 1979-1982, 13 folders (Box 10)
    - Recent Correspondence
      - A Correspondence
        - 1983-1993 (Box 16)
        - 1994-1998 (Box 16)
          lacking 1996
      - B Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1998, 4 folders (Box 16)
        - Barnes, Helen 1992-1993 (Box 16)
      - C Correspondence 1983-1999, 5 folders (Box 16)
      - D Correspondence 1983-1999, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - E Correspondence
        - 1983-1987 (Box 16)
        - 1988-1999 (Box 16)
          lacking 1996 and 1998
      - F Correspondence
        - 1983-1989 (Box 16)
        - 1990-2000 (Box 16)
          lacking 1999
      - G Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1983-1990, 2 folders (Box 17)
          - 1991-1999 (Box 17)
            lacking 1997
        - Gill/St. Bernard Schools 1978-1979 (Box 17)
      - H Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1983-1999, 3 folders (Box 17)
        - Hampson, Christopher 1991-1992 (Box 17)
        - Hawaii 1978-1981 (Box 17)
        - Horn, Wade F. 1991-1994 (Box 17)
          lacking 1993
      - I, J Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1997, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Johnson, George 1987, 1989-1993, 1996 (Box 17)
          lacking 1991-1992
      - K Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1998, 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Kagan, Sharon Lynn 1986-1989, 1995 (Box 17)
        - Kimble, Deborah G. 1992, 1994-1995 (Box 17)
      - L Correspondence
        - 1983-1985 (Box 17)
        - 1987-1999 (Box 17)
          lacking 1998
      - M Correspondence
        - 1983-1989, 4 folders (Box 17)
        - 1992-1999, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - N, O Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1999 (Box 18)
        - National Association for the Education of Young Children (1993) (Box 18)
        - National Center for Education Statistics 1985 (Box 18)
      - P, Q Correspondence 1983-1998, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - R Correspondence
        - 1983-1989 (Box 18)
        - 1990-1999 (Box 18)
      - S Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983-1999, 6 folders (Box 18)
        - Sagawa, Shirley 1988-1998 (Box 18)
        - Society for Research in Child Development 1976 (Box 18)
      - T Correspondence
        - 1983-1986 1989 (Box 18)
        - 1990, 1993-1999 (Box 18)
      - U, V Correspondence 1983, 1985-1999 (Box 18)
        lacking 1987, 1994, and 1998
      - W Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1983-1987 (Box 18)
          - 1988-1992 (Box 19)
          - 1993-1999 (Box 19)
        - Williams, Betty 1980-1989, 1993, 1996 (Box 19)
      - X, Y, Z Correspondence
        - Miscellaneous 1983, 1985-1990, 1993, 1995, 1999 (Box 19)
        - Young, Mary E. 1996-1999 (Box 19)
        - Zigler, Edward 1992-1994, 1999 (Box 19)
    - International Correspondence
      - Chile
        - 1973-1974 (Box 19)
        - 1975-1979 (Box 19)
          lacking 1978
      - Colombia
        - 1970-1974, 5 folders (Box 19)
        - 1975-1977 1980 (Box 19)
      - England
        - Miscellaneous
          - 1969-1974 1978-1980 (Box 19)
            lacking 1973
          - 1981-1988, 3 folders (Box 19)
        - Aga Khan Foundation 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Blackwell, Frank
          - 1979-1981, 2 folders (Box 19)
          - 1982-1991, 6 folders (Box 20)
        - Gulbenkian Foundation U. K. Branch 1979-1988 (Box 20)
        - National Children Bureau 1979-1989 (Box 20)
          lacking 1980
      - Germany 1977 (Box 20)
      - Netherlands
        - Bernard van Leer Foundation 1977-1991, 8 folders (Box 20)
      - Portugal
        - Gulbenkian Foundation 1979-1986 (Box 20)
      - Scotland 1979-1981 (Box 20)
  - Writings and speeches
    - Articles published
      - 1963 1966-1968 (Box 21)
      - 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - 1974 1976-1977 (Box 21)